section 2 Chapter 9 B When he woke it was with the sensation
of having slept for a long time, but to glance at the old-fashioned clock
told him that it was only twenty Thirty He lay dozing for a while;
then the usual deep lunged singing struck up from the yard below:
It was only an hopeless fancy, It passed like an April die But a look and a word
in the dreams they stood They have stolen my heart away The dribbling song seems to have kept
its popularity.
You still heard it all over the place. It had outlived the Hate Song.
Julia woke at the sound, stretched herself luxuriously and got out of bed.
'I'm hungry,' she said. 'Let's make some more coffee.
Damn! The stove's gone out and the water's cold.'
She picked the stove up and shook it.
'There's no oil in it.'
'We can get some from old Charrington, I expect funny thing is I made sure it was full.
I'm going to put my clothes on,' she added.
'It seems to have got colder.'
Winston also got up and dressed himself in The fatigable voice sang on I saw
that time heals all things, They say you can always forget;
But the smiles and the tears across the years They twist my art strings yet!
As he fastens the belt of his overalls he strolled across to the window
sun must have gone down behind the houses; it was not shining into the yard
any longer. The flagstones were wet as though they had just been washed, and he
had the feeling that the sky had been washed too, so fresh and pale was the
blue between the chimney pots. Tirelessly the woman marched to and fro Caulking
and uncorking herself, singing and falling silent, and pegging out more
diapers, and more and yet more.
He wondered whether she took in washing for a living, or was merely the slave of
20 or 30 grandchildren.
Julia had come across to his side; together they gazed down with a sort of
fascination of the sturdy figure below.
As he looked at the woman in her characteristic attitude the thick arms
reaching up for the line, her powerful mayor-like buttocks protruded, it struck
him for the first time that she was beautiful.
It had never before occurred to him that the body of a woman of 50 blown up to
monstrous dimensions by childbearing, then hardened, roughened by work till it
was coarse in the grain like an overripe turn it could be beautiful.
But it was so, and after all, he thought, why not?
The solid, contourless body, like a block of granite, and the rasping red skin, bore
the same relation to the body of a girl as the rosehip to the rose.
Why should the fruit be held inferior to the flower?
'She's beautiful,' he murmured.
'She's a meter across the hips, easily,' said Julia.
'That is her style of beauty,' said Winston.
He held Julius supple waste easily encircled by his arm.
From the hip to the knee her flank was against his. Out of their bodies no child
would ever come.
That was the one thing they could never do.
Only by word of mouth, from mind to mind, could they pass on the secret.
The woman down there had no mind, she had only strong arms, a warm heart and a
fertile belly.
He wondered how many children she had given birth to.
It might easily be 15. She had had her momentary flowering, a year, perhaps, of
Wild Rose beauty, and then she had suddenly swollen like a fertilized fruit
and grown hard and red and coarse, and then her life had been laundering,
scrubbing, darning, cooking, sweeping, polishing, mending, scrubbing, laundering,
first for children, then for grandchildren, over 30 unbroken years.
At the end of it she was still singing.
The mystical reverence that he felt for her was somehow mixed up with the aspect
of the pale, cloudless sky, stretching away behind the chimney pots into interminable distance
It was curious to think that the sky was the same for everybody, in Eurasia or
East Asia as well as here.
And the people under the sky were also very much the same—
—everywhere, all over the world, hundreds of thousands of millions of people just
like this, people ignorant of one another's existence, held apart by walls
of hatred and lies, and yet almost exactly the same— —people who had never learned to think
but who was soaring up in their hearts and bellies and muscles the power that
would one day overturn the world.
If there was hope, it lay in the proles!
Without having read to the end of the book, he knew that that must be Goldstein's final message.
The future belongs to the pros And could he be sure that when their
time came the world they constructed would not be just as alien to him,
Winston Smith, as the world of the Party?
Yes, because at the least it would be a world of sanity.
Where there is equality there can be sanity.
Sooner or later it would happen, strength would change into consciousness. The
pearls were immortal, you could not doubt it when you looked at that valiant figure in the yard.
In the end their awakening would come.
And until that happened, though it might be a thousand years, they would stay
alive against all the odds, like birds, passing on from body to body the
vitality which the Party did not share and could not kill.
'Do you remember,' he said, 'the thrush that sang to us, that first day, at the edge of
the wood?'
'He wasn't singing to us,' said Julia. 'He was singing to please himself. Not even
that. He was just singing.'
The birds sang, the pearls sang, the Party did not sing. All Around the world, in
London and New York, in Africa and Brazil and in the mysterious, forbidden lands
beyond the frontiers, in the streets of Paris and Berlin, in the villages of the
endless Russian plain, in the bazaars of China and Japan— —everywhere stood the
same solid unconquerable figure, made monstrous by work and childbearing,
toiling from birth to death and still singing. Out of those mighty loins a race
of conscious beings must one day come.
You were the dead; theirs was the future that you could share in that future if
you kept alive the mind as they kept alive the body, and passed on the secret
doctrine that two plus two make four.
'We are the dead,' he said.
'We are the dead,' echoed Julia dutifully.
'You are the dead see denying voice behind them.
They sprang apart. Winston's entrails seemed to have turned into ice.
He could see the white all around the irises of Julia's eyes.
Her face had turned to milky yellow. The smear of rouge that was still on each
cheekbone stood out sharply, almost as though unconnected with the skin beneath.
'You are the dead,' repeated the iron voice.
'It was behind the picture,' breathed Julia.
'It was behind the picture,' said the voice.
'Remain exactly where you are.
Make no movement until you are ordered.'
It was starting, it was starting at last!
They could do nothing except stand gazing into one another's eyes.
To run for life, to get out of the house before it was too late— —no such thought
occurred to them.
Unthinkable to disobey the ion voice from the wall.
There was a snap as though a catch had been turned back, and a crash of breaking glass.
The picture had fallen to the floor, uncovering the telescreen behind it
and see us,' said Julia.
'Now we can see you,' said the voice.
'Stand out in the middle of the room.
Stand back to back. Clasp your hands behind your heads. Do not touch one another.'
They were not touching, but it seemed to him that he could feel Julia's body shaking.
Or perhaps it was merely the shaking of his own. He could just stop his teeth
from chattering, but his knees were beyond his control.
There was a sound of trampling boots below, inside the house and outside. The
yard seemed to be full of men.
Something was being dragged across the stones. The woman's singing had stopped
abruptly. There was a long, rolling clang, as though the wash tub had been flunked
across the yard, and then a confusion of angry shouts which ended in a yell of pain.
'The house is surrounded,' said Winston.
'The house is surrounded,' said the voice.
He heard Julia snap her teeth together.
'I suppose we may as well say goodbye she said.
'You may as well say goodbye said the voice.
And then another quite different voice, a thin, cultivated voice which Winston had
the impression of having heard before, struck in: 'And by the way, while we are on the subject,
"Here comes a candle to light you to bed, here comes a chopper to chop off your head!"'
Something crashed onto the bed behind Winston's back. The head of a ladder had
been thrust through the window and had burst in the frame.
Someone was climbing through the window.
There was a stampede of boots up the stairs. The room was full of solid men in
black uniforms, with iron shot boots on their feet and trunches in their hands.
Winston was not trembling any longer.
Even his eyes he barely moved.
One thing alone mattered: to keep still, to keep still and not give them an
excuse to hit you!
A man with a smooth prize Fighters jowl in which the mouth was only a slit
paused opposite him, balancing his truncheon meditatively between thumb and forefinger.
Winston met his eyes.
The feeling of nakedness, with one's hands behind one's head and one's face
and body all exposed, was almost unbearable.
The man protruded the tip of a white tongue linked to the place where his
lips should have been and then passed on.
There was another crash. Someone had picked up the glass paperweight from the
table and smashed it to pieces on the hearthstone.
The fragment of coral, a tiny crinkle of pink like a sugar rosebud from a cake,
rolled across the mat.
How small, thought Winston, how small it always was!
There was a gasp and a thump behind him, and he received a violent kick on the
ankle which nearly flung him off his ballads One of the men had smashed his fist into
Julia's solar plexus, doubling her up like a pocket ruler. She was thrashing
about on the floor, fighting for breath.
Winston and dared not turn his head even by a millimeter but sometimes her liver
to gasping face came within the angle of his vision.
Even in his terror it was as though he could feel the pain in his own body, the
deadly pain which nevertheless was less urgent than the struggle to get back her breath.
He knew what it was like: the terrible, agonizing pain which was
there all the while but could not be suffered yet, because before all else it
was necessary to be able to breathe.
Then two of the men hoisted her up by knees and shoulders and carried her out
of the room like a sack.
Winston had a glimpse of her face, upside down, yellow and contorted, with the eyes
shut, and still with the smear of rouge on either cheek;
and that was the last he saw of her.
He stood dead still. No one had hit him yet.
Thoughts which came of their own accord but seemed totally uninteresting began
to flit through his mind.
He wondered whether they had got Mr tarrington He wondered what they had done to the
woman in the yard.
He noticed that he badly wanted to urinate, and felt a faint surprise,
because he had done so only two or three hours ago.
He noticed that the clock on the mantelpiece said nine, meaning 21 But the
light seemed too strong. Would not the light be fading at 21 hours on an August evening?
He wondered whether after all he and Julia had mistaken the time it slipped
the clock round and thought it was 20 30 when really it was not 8 30 on the
following morning.
But he did not pursue the thought further. It was not interesting.
There was another, lighter step in the passage. Mr Charrington came into the
room. The demeanor of the black uniformed men suddenly became more subdued.
Something had also changed in Mr cherrington's appearance.
His eye fell on the fragments of the glass paperweight.
'Pick up those pieces,' he said sharply.
A man stooped to obey. The cockney accent had disappeared; Winston suddenly
realized whose voice it was that he had heard a few moments ago on the telescreen.
Mr Charrington was still wearing his old velvet jacket, but his hair, which had
been almost white, had turned black.
Also he was not wearing his spectacles.
He gave Winston a single sharp glance, as though verifying his identity, and then
paid no more attention to him.
He was still recognizable but he was not the same person any longer. His body had
straightened, and seemed to have grown bigger.
His face had undergone only tiny changes that had nevertheless worked to complete
transformation. The black eyebrows were less bushy, the wrinkles were gone, the
whole lines of the face seemed to have altered; even the nose seemed shorter.
It was the alert, cold face of a man of about 5 and 30.
It occurred to Winston that for the first time in his life he was looking,
with knowledge, at a member of the Thought Police